okay let's work on the solution for our
rob timing quiz this time so the
question is when does the add and
multiply issue and when do they commit
for issue the ad will try to issue in
the third cycle if we have a reservation
station available and we do because we
are currently using both of the multiply
divide reservation station but the add
one is free so the add issues in cycle
three
and the next instruction multiplication
will try to issue in cycle four the
question is whether we have a free
reservation station
indeed we do because we have begun
executing the multiplication in cycle
three here that has freed one of the two
reservation stations we were holding
so pretty much at cycle four both of the
multiply divided reservation stations
are actually available so we can issue
in cycle four let's now put this here so
we have three and four when does this
execute because to figure out the commit
we actually have to figure out also when
do they execute and write results the
add uses r7 and r8 those are not written
by any of the previous instructions so
the ad can actually begin execution in
cycle four and because it takes only one
cycle it will try to write the result in
circle five now the multiplication is
already writing the result in cycle five
but we said
that we can broadcast one add result and
one multiply result in the same cycle
this is a multiply this is a divide so
they can actually go in the same cycle
so this will broadcast the result also
in cycle five now let's see what happens
with the multiplication here it issues
in cycle 4 it uses r1 and r2
so it actually cannot execute until both
of those results have been written by
instructions divide and multiply here so
we have to wait for the later of these
two which is cycle six that's when we
dispatch we can begin execution in cycle
seven
this is a multiplication takes two
cycles
so in cycles seven and eight it's
executing in cycle 9
it will write its result now we are
ready to figure out the commit
we said that we can commit up to two
instructions per cycle
in cycle 8 we are committing the
multiplication here the question is can
we commit another instruction in that
same cycle because normally we could if
that instruction is done and indeed it
is because this instruction has been
ready to commit since cycle five all it
was waiting for is for the commit point
to reach there so in cycle eight here we
will commit it does the correct answer
for the commit here is 8
and now finally we need to figure out
when does the multiplication commit well
it cannot commit in cycle 9 because it
doesn't have a result
written yet then but it will try to
commit in cycle 10 and by that time
previous instructions have committed we
have a result so indeed it commits in
cycle 10.
so we can write 10 here